Guide to the Eli L. Oliver papers, 1927-1968 MS2114
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Eli L. Oliver papers
1927-1968
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Oliver, Eli, L.
MS2114
8.5 Linear Feet
Eli Oliver was an organizer for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of American in its Western Department from 1923-1928. For nine years, from 1928-37, he directed the research department of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks and represented the United Textile Workers on the Textile Work Assignment Board of the National Recovery Administration from 1934-35. In 1937, he became executive vice-president of Labor's Non-Partisan League. Oliver left the Non-Partisan League in 1940 and became the executive director of the American Labor Party of New York for the 1940 election campaign. Collection contains correspondence, hearing exhibits, financial reports, campaign literature and posters, reports, expense accounts, photographs, newspaper articles, speeches, press releases, pamphlets, and publications. The material dates from 1927-68.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Aquisition information is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
Eli L. Oliver (b. 1899) was born in Walker, Minnesota and graduated from the University of Minnesota in 1918. His career in the labor field as an organizer and teacher began on the staff of the Federal Trade Commission in 1918 and again in 1920. From 1920-21 he was on the faculty of the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania and taught evenings at the Philadelphia Labor College. The following year he taught at Brookwood Labor College, Katonah, New York. He later worked as director of Labor Bureau, Inc. serving in its Philadelphia, New York, Chicago, and San Francisco offices.
In 1923, Oliver represented the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union in Cleveland on the Joint Bureau of Standards, setting production standards for the garment industry. From 1923-28 he was an organizer for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of American in its Western Department. For nine years, from 1928-37, he directed the research department of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks and represented the United Textile Workers on the Textile Work Assignment Board of the National Recovery Administration from 1934-35. In 1937, he became executive vice-president of Labor's Non-Partisan League. Oliver left the Non-Partisan League in 1940 and became the executive director of the American Labor Party of New York for the 1940 election campaign. Following his work for the American Labor Party, Oliver joined the Labor Relations Branch of the Labor Division of the Office of Production Management (later to become the War Production Board) working as Special Labor Assistant to Sidney Hillman. In 1942, he became head of the Washington, D.C. office of the Labor Bureau of the Middle West and remained there until 1971. While he was with this organization, Oliver was Secretary-Treasurer of Labor's committee for Truman and Barkley in 1948 and Labor's committee for Stevenson and Sparkman in 1952.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, hearing exhibits, financial reports, campaign literature and posters, reports, expense accounts, photographs, newspaper articles, speeches, press releases, pamphlets, and publications. The material dates from 1927-68.
The collection is rich in materials for the study of labor's involvement in politics from the 1930s to 1952. The correspondence contains letters from union officials from around the country for this period. Material related to Labor's Non-Partisan League includes financial records, organization memos, campaign pamphlets, and press releases. Also included are reports discussing primary and general election strategies form 1938 and 1940. Similar material is present for the American Labor Party of New York relating to the 1940 campaign and for the Labor Committee's backing the Truman-Barkley and Stevenson-Sparkman campaigns in 1948 and 1952. The Brotherhood of Railway Clerks is also represented within the collection material. There is also some personal materials for Oliver including photographs and financial records.
Photographs; Labor; Labor and laboring classes; Labor unions; American Labor Party of the State of New York; Oliver, Eli, L.; Labor's Non-Partisan League; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1936-08/1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 09/1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 09/1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 09/1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 09/1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 09/1940-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Publications, 1924 ca.-1952 ca. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous Publications, 1924 ca.-1952 ca. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Financial, 1935-1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1927-1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1927-1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearings and Exhibits, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Wage Hearing Exhibits, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Brotherhood of Railway Clerks--Publications, 1922-1938 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Labor's'Non-Partisan League---Financial, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports; Statements, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports; Statements, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports; Statements, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports; Statements, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Pamphlets, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Primaries, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Primaries, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Proposed Plans for 1940 Campaign, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Proposed Plans for 1940 Campaign, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Publications--National Bulletin, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Labor'-s Non-Partisan League--Publications--Legislative News, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Labor's Non-Partisan League--Statistics on Congress, 1938-1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- American Labor Party--Financial, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- American Labor-Party--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- American Labor-Party--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- American Labor Party--1940 Campaign Material, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- American Labor Party--State Committee Meeting Report, 09/14/1940 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- American Labor Party--New York State Convention Report, 09/28/1940 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- American Labor Party--Charles E. Ervin, "What Really Happened in the National Campaign of 1940", undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
- American Labor Party--Publications American Labor Part News various issues, 08/1940-11/1940 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Office of Production Management--Expense Account, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Office of Production Management--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1941-1942 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Office of Production Management--Miscellaneous Reports, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Office of Production Management--Wage Stabilization Meetings, 01/1942--03/1942 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Labor's Committee for Truman and Barkley--Financial, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Labor's Committee for Truman and Barkley--"Get Out the Vote Contest", 1948 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Labor's Committee for Truman and Barkley--Advertising Mats, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Labor's Committee for Truman and Barkley--Memos, Reports, Statements, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Labor's Committee for Truman and Barkley--Press Releases, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Financial, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Financial, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--"Get Out the Vote Contest", 1952 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Memos, Reports, Releases, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Memos, Reports, Releases, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Memos, Reports, Releases, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Posters and Pamphlets, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--Posters and Pamphlets 1952 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--"Text of Eisenhower Speeches", 1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Labor's Committee for Stevenson and Sparkman--"Text of Stevenson Speeches", 1952 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Labor League of the Middle West--"Report to the Government of India on Various Aspects of Industrial Relations on the Railroads of India", 1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Oliver--Personal--Financial, 1927-1952 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Oliver--Personal--Miscellany", undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Oliver--Personal--Newspaper Clippings, 1927 ca.-1952 ca. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Oliver--Personal--Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Addenda to Office of Production Management Memos, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Addenda to Office of Production Management Memos, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Speeches, Addresses, 1937-1942 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Legal Study of the National Recovery Administration, 1937, undated (Box 12)
- Legal Study of the National Recovery Administration, 1937, undated (Box 13)
- Papers, undated (Box 14)
- Labor's League for Stevenson and Sparkman--Campaign Posters, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 1)